So today's דף *Daf* is מ"ב *Mem-Beis*, and guess which we're up
to? מ"ב *Mem-Beis*. We pick up on מ"ב *Mem-Beis* עמוד א' *Amud
Aleph*,
five lines from the top, תניא אידך tanya idach, *Tanya Idach*. So
now we are in the middle of actually different things that we
learn from the פסוק Pasuk *Pasuk* בעל השור נקי Ba'al Hashor Naki
*Ba'al HaShor Naki* telling you about the case of the goring ox
that you stone it, but
you don't pay כופר Kofer, *Kofer*. But if it does it three
times, then גם בעליו יומת *Gam Ba'alav Yumat* which we say is
מיתה בידי שמים *Mita bi-ydei shamayim* and you pay כופר Kofair *Kofer*
which atones for the מיתה בידי שמים *Mita bi-ydei shamayim*. But anyway,
the first three times בעל השור נקי Ba'al Hashor Naki *Ba'al HaShor
Naki*, you don't have any liability personally or you don't deserve punishment,
but חז"ל *Chazal* read that to be telling you something else other
than that. So the first thing we talked about was that it
teaches you that you can't drive any benefit or you can't even
drive any benefit from the leather. Okay, and רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
*Rabbi Eliezer* learned it out to tell you that you don't have
to pay half כופר Kofer, *Kofer*, to which רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
*Rabbi Akiva* said, how can you pay half כופר kofer, *Kofer*? If
you're stoning the ox, then the idea of half is an idea
of a תם Tam *Tam* and that's paying מגופא *Migufah*. Okay, but
that was the last thing we learned out from it was the
idea that you're exempt from half כופר kofer, *Kofer* for תם Tam,
*Tam*. So the rest of today's דף *Daf* is going to be
about things we learn out from בעל השור נקי Ba'al Hashor Naki.
*Ba'al HaShor Naki*. Let's take a look. תניא אידך *Tanya Idach*, we
taught in another ברייתא Braisa *Baraita*: בעל השור נקי Ba'al Hashor Naki?
*Ba'al HaShor Naki*, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei HaGelili *Rabbi Yose HaGelili*
אומר *omer*, נקי מדמי ולדות Vlodot *Naki midmei vladot*. That if it
gores a pregnant woman, so we know later in
משפטים *Mishpatim* if a man hits a pregnant woman and she miscarries,
you pay the assessment of that, the damages of that to the
husband. So let's say an ox gores a pregnant woman. So maybe
you should also pay. Now the reality is, the interesting thing is
you do pay, I mean if an ox gores a woman, right,
you pay the damages. But there you pay the damages like in
a way this is like the abortion debate, like whose body is
it? Like so there you would pay the damages to the woman's
body. So you would sort of like assess, like how much has
the woman's body been injured as a result of this? And it
might actually be now you say well, you know, on the slave
market the body is worth less because, you know, if you were
to sell a pregnant woman you'd also get paid for the future
slaves, right? So how much do you assess the damage to the
body as the loss of the fetus? And it seems like you
don't. It seems like to determine נזק Nezek. *Nezek* to the woman's
body you just sort of ask yourself well like, is she injured
or not? Like you know, if basically it was a miscarriage but
otherwise she's okay and she's not injured and she's, you know, and
so her body would still sell for the same thing it would
had she been before she had been pregnant on the slave market.
So then there would not be any payment of damages to the
woman's body. The only payment would be would be for the loss
of the fetus. Okay, and that is what you pay in the
Torah says: כאשר ישית עליו בעל האשה ונתן בפלילים *Kasher yashit alav
ba'al ha'ishah venatan biflilim* when the miscarriage is, you assess not only
the damage to the woman's body but the loss of the fetus.
And for some reason by the goring ox you're not going to
pay that, and we learned about that about בעל השור נקי Ba'al
Hashor Naki *Ba'al HaShor Naki* because this has nothing to do with,
I mean with that case, I mean it sort of does a
little because it's about a loss of life, life for the fetus.
But it's really just learning out another thing. There are all these
payments, but there's some other case that you don't have to pay
for an ox. What is the case you don't have to pay
for an ox? In a case of what you know, the loss
of the fetus. Of course I still don't really fully understand that
because I don't understand why the value of the woman is not
affected by the fact that she's pregnant or not pregnant, but that's
the הלכה Halacha. *Halakha*, so that's actually quite a strange exemption, at
least I think. Yes.
Is the loss of the fetus specifically?
No, you mean no, I'm no we're talking about like the actual
value loss in the slave market. A pregnant woman would go for
more, a pregnant slave would go for more than a non-pregnant slave
in the slave market. But for some reason we don't figure that
as the loss of value in the woman's body, and we just
assess the
fetus independently and that's only paid by a case when a human
causes a miscarriage and not when an ox causes a miscarriage.
Is there psychological damages?
Yeah, I mean in a case of human damage then there is,
then there's the pain and the suffering and all of that. In
a case where a human does it, not in a case where
an ox does it. Yes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this: רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose HaGelili* אומר *omer*, נקי מדמי
ולדות *Naki midmei vladot*. So if an ox does it, it doesn't
pay for the cost of the fetus. אמר לו *Amar lo* רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*, הרי אומר *harei omer*, כי ינצו אנשים
Ki yinatzu anashim, *ki inatzu anashim* when people fight and then it
speaks about smiting a pregnant woman. אנשים ולא שוורים Anashim v'lo shvarim.
*Anashim velo shevarim*, people and not oxen. So we can learn from
that פרשה Parsha *Parsha* that it's only a special payment for a
case of when people fight. שפיר קאמר *Shapir kama'ei* רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva? *Rabbi Akiva*. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva* has all
these critiques about different דרשות Derashot *Drashot* of בעל השור נקי Ba'al
Hashor Naki *Ba'al HaShor Naki*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying
that is a good critique, what would רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose
HaGelili* say back? אמר רב עולא בריה דרב אידי *Amar Rav Ulla
brei d'Rav Idi*, איצטריך Itstrich. *itzrich*. No, you still need it even
though you have אנשים ולא שוורים Anashim v'lo shvarim *anashim velo shevarim*.
סלקא דעתך אמינא Salka daitach amina, *Salka da'atach amina*, I would have
thought by that case about the direct case about the miscarriage, אנשים
ולא שוורים Anashim v'lo shvarim. *anashim velo shevarim*, אדומים לאנשים *adumim lanashim*.
אדומים וחמורים *Adumim v'chamurim*.
Exactly, if
people pay but not oxen when they're acting like people. an ox
acting like people מה אנשים Anashim מועדין the same way a person
is always considered מועד Muad habitual full damages אף שוורים מועדין Af
shvarim muadin so when an ox is a מועד Muad ox then
it won't pay for the loss of the fetus okay, because then
it's comparable to the אנשים Anashim, case. התם Hatam but if the
ox was a תם Tam which is what we're talking about, right,
we're talking about a case as all בעל השור נקי Ba'al Hashor
Naki is by a תם, Tam if we're talking about a תם
Tam then מחייב. Mechayev. Wait why would a תם Tam be? Of
course that's going to be the question coming up. Then I might
think you would pay because that's not excluded by the words אנשים
ולא שוורים. Anashim v'lo shvarim. כתב רחמנא בעל השור נקי, Katav Rachmana
Ba'al Hashor Naki, it says בעל השור נקי Ba'al Hashor Naki, by
a תם Tam to say דפטור De'pattur that you're exempt even in
a case of a תם Tam by the miscarriage. So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so of course the question is
obvious: יתיבא בארעא וגיורא בשמי שמיא? Yativa b'ara v'giyura bishmei shamaya? What,
the citizen is on the land and the and the like the
stranger is up in the heavens? Meaning it's like the it's crazy,
this is upside down. So how could it be that a מועד
Muad is totally פטור Pattur when you would have thought that a
תם Tam would be חייב? Chayiv? In the end they're both פטור,
Pattur, but how could you even have thought that? אלא אמר רבא,
Ella Amar Rava, rather רבא Rava said איצטריך. Now here's why you
need even though you have אנשים ולא שוורים Anashim v'lo shvarim, a
separate
פסוק Pasuk of בעל השור נקי. Ba'al Hashor Naki סלקא דעתך אמינא,
I would have thought
אנשים ולא שוורים אדומים לאנשים, Anashim v'lo shvarim adumin l'anashim, same like
you said, it would have excluded a מועד Muad ox. וטפי קאמר
לתם, V'tapi ka'amar l'tam, and once it says a מועד Muad ox
doesn't pay for miscarriage, I would have said a תם Tam, also
doesn't pay for miscarriage. Fine. So I have it all from כי
ינצו אנשים, Ki yinatzu anashim, why do I need בעל השור נקי?
Ba'al Hashor Naki Because let's keep on going, okay, דפטירי. De'ptiri. הדר
כתב רחמנא בעל השור נקי, Hadar katav Rachmana Ba'al Hashor Naki, but
then it says בעל השור נקי Ba'al Hashor Naki, in a case
of תם Tam, to clarify, not to tell you you're exempt. You
already know you're exempt from אנשים ולא שוורים. Anashim v'lo shvarim But
בעל השור נקי Ba'al Hashor Naki is clarifying really the only case
that's exempt is the שור תם. Shor Tam. Okay, דבעל השור נקי
תם פטור מועד חייב. De'Ba'al Hashor Naki tam pattur muad chayiv. So
actually here we're saying a different הלכה. Halacha? We're saying בעל השור
נקי Ba'al Hashor Naki is to tell you the only case you're
פטור Pattur for the ולדות is a case of a תם, Tam.
but a מועד Muad is actually חייב Chayiv for דמי ולדות, Dmei
vlodot, which I'm happy with that, we're not going to end that
way but I'm happy with that conclusion because to me it makes
sense you should be paying דמי ולדות Dmei vlodot like it's very
bizarre that that's not just considered a straight נזק. Nezek Yes. Go.
Is this some kind of כלל ופרט Klal u'prat or is it
just a סברא? Sevara? In other words, is it kind of a
general principle and then a clarification to denote an exception?
Oh yeah, I mean to some degree, a
hermeneutic like
similar to כלל ופרט Klal u'prat but obviously it's very different because
here it's all based on דרשות as opposed to כלל ופרט Klal
u'prat which is very much explicit in the פסוקים Psukim and their
very concrete cases and so on. But you're right, it's using one
פסוק Pasuk. to clarify another, so that is it's similar in that
way. Okay, so therefore actually what this is telling you is not
that you're פטור Pattur by a תם, Tam that you're right I
knew, it's actually telling you you're חייב Chayiv by a
מועד. Muad. Okay. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye
said, אלא מעתה Ella me'ata if that's what you're going to do
to make the דרשה, Drasha, גבי בושת נמי, Gabi boshet nami, let's
say the same by בושת. Boshet. Let's get an ox that's a
מועד Muad to pay בושת. Boshet. How are we going to do
that?
נימא הכי, Neima hachi, say the same thing. אנשים ולא שוורים. Anashim
v'lo shvarim It says by בושת, Boshet, right, about people fighting and
the woman grabbing the privates of the of the other man, right?
כי ינצו אנשים, Ki yinatzu anashim? right? כי ינצו אנשים? Ki yinatzu
anashim I think it's כי ינצו. Ki yinatzu. וקרבה
אשת האחד להציל את אישה מיד מכהו,
V'karva eshet ha'echad l'hatzil
et
isha miyad makehu, miyad, anyway. Okay,
anyway,
it's also כי ינצו אנשים Anashim and there it says about, so
we'll say אנשים ולא שוורים, Anashim velo shevarim, that's the פרשה Parsha.
where we learn בושת Boshet from, and we'll say and we know
that an ox doesn't pay בושת Boshet because it says אנשים, Anashim
but let's come to a similar conclusion that maybe a מועד Muad
will pay בושת. Boshet. How are we come to that conclusion? The
following way: נימא הכי אנשים מועדים אף שוורים מועדים. Neima hachi anashim
muadim af shvarim muadim. וקל וחומר לתם דפטירי. V'kal vachomer l'tam d'ptiri.
So I would learn from there that oxen are exempt, מועד Muad
and certainly a תם. Tam, הדר כתב רחמנא בעל השור נקי, Hadar
katav Rachmana Ba'al Hashor Naki, and then it says בעל השור נקי,
Ba'al Hashor Naki so בעל השור נקי Ba'al Hashor Naki, should tell
me תם פטור, Tam pattur, there are cases where, you know, where
only it's only the תם Tam that's פטור. Pattur. In this case
like בעל השור נקי Ba'al Hashor Naki. which is a תם, Tam
only the תם tam, is פטור, Pattur, ומועד חייב, V'muad chayiv, and
a מועד Muad would be חייב. Chayiv. So בעל השור נקי, Baal
hashor naki there's no indication there that we're talking about a miscarriage,
of course you could say that the whole concept here is a
loss of life, but basically if that's what you're doing, בעל השור
נקי Baal hashor naki is to tell you no, no, no, you
thought every ox was פטור, Pattur, it's only the תם tam that's
פטור, Pattur, the מועד Muad is still going to be חייב. Chayiv.
So if you're going to say apply that to the case of
אנשים ולא שוורים Anashim velo shevarim by דמי ולדות, Dmei vlodot, you
should say it by אנשים ולא שוורים Anashim velo shevarim. by בושת.
Boshet. I don't see why. What just makes you pick one more
than the other?
Because בושת Boshet was a different פרשה. Parsha This isn't דמי ולדות.
Dmei vlodot. I don't
understand.
They're two separate cases that talk about people fighting, one is a
miscarriage and one is a בושת Boshet case, right? Neither of which
are being talked about in this פסוק. Pasuk So if we're using
בעל השור נקי Baal hashor naki to reference a פסוק Pasuk talking
about people fighting and a miscarriage, it should also be able to
reference people fighting in a בושת Boshet case. The only thing I
would say is what I said before, that... at least in the
miscarriage it's a context of a loss of life. Okay, but if
you're using בעל השור נקי Ba'al ha-shor naki to reference some distant
case of miscarriage and to tell you that a מועד Mo'ed is
חייב, Chayav, have it reference a distant case of בושת Bosheth and
have it tell you that מועד Mo'ed is חייב. Chayav. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says הדא דקאמר בעל השור נקי פטור מדמי ולדות.
Hada dekamar Ba'al Hashor Naki patur midmei velados. ואי תימא הכי נמי.
Ve'ei teima hachi nami. You know what, maybe not. I mean, let's
say why not? Let's say that a שור מועד Shor Mo'ed would
pay for בושת. Bosheth. אי הכי, Ei hachi, if that's what we're
trying to say, ליתני בעל השור נקי רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר פטור
מדמי ולדות ומבושת. Lisni Ba'al Hashor Naki Rabbi Yosei HaGelili omer patur
midmei velados umibosheth. Have רבי יוסי הגלילי say בושת Bosheth as well.
Okay,
so this is not really a critique of this general idea. You
actually said, you know, in terms of working with the פסוקים, Psukim,
אנשים ולא שוורים, Anashim velo shevarim. בעל השור נקי, Ba'al ha-shor naki
it worked okay, and we were able to actually come to what
I consider to be a very reasonable conclusion, which is that a
שור מועד Shor Mo'ed should pay for דמי ולדות, Dmei Velados, but
the only point is, yeah, but then why are you picking דמי
ולדות Dmei Velados more than anything else? You could have easily also
included a בושת Bosheth discussion in that. Okay, so אביי Abaye doesn't
like it. So let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. אלא אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו, Ella Abaye veRava de'amri tarvaihu,
here's what we're going to do. Again, the problem is not to
say that an ox is exempt from דמי ולדות, Dmei Velados, but
the problem is to say that don't you already have a פסוק
Pasuk that says אנשים ולא שוורים Anashim velo shevarim to tell you
the same הלכה? Halacha So now we're going to find something else
to do with that דרשה Derasha of אנשים ולא שוורים. Anashim vlo
shvarim So אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו, Abaye veRava de'amri tarvaihu, אנשים אין
אסון באשה יענשו. Anashim ein ason be'ishah ye'aneshu. Right,
the פסוק Pasuk there says, right, what does it say? וכי ינצו
אנשים ונגפו אשה הרה ויצאו ילדיה ולא יהיה אסון ענוש יענש כאשר
ישית עליו בעל האשה. Vechi yinatzu anashim venagefu ishah harah veyatzu yeladeiha
velo yihyeh ason anosh ye'anesh ka'asher yashis alav ba'al ha'ishah. There's no
tragedy. ענוש יענש כאשר ישית עליו בעל האשה. Anosh ye'anesh ka'asher yashis
alav ba'al ha'ishah. Now, what is the point of saying that there's
no... ואם אסון יהיה ונתת נפש תחת נפש. Ve'im ason yihyeh venasata
nefesh tachas nafesh. If there's a tragedy, a loss of life, somebody
actually got killed, not just the fetus, but a born person got
killed, then obviously you put the person to death, which is obviously
a challenging פסוק Pasuk, because it sounds like it would have been
an accident. It sounds like you're executing somebody for
accidental homicide or whatever. The... By the way, once we're talking about
that פסוק, Pasuk it's worth knowing that the church, the Catholic church,
because of the translation of the Septuagint, came up with their position
about abortion. Because they read the Septuagint reads the word אסון, Ason,
not meaning tragedy, but formed. Okay? ולא יהיה אסון, Velo yihyeh ason,
the fetus is not yet formed. But אם אסון יהיה, Im ason
yihyeh, I have no idea how the Septuagint got that, but if
the fetus is formed, then it's an act of murder. And the
Catholic church, you know, they knew their Bible through the Septuagint, through
the Greek. So anyway, that actually led to their position
on abortion? Yeah, I don't know, I don't know what the basis
of that translation is. But it is based on that translation, certainly.
It seems to us like a mistranslation. Anyway, so here's how they're
reading the אנשים ולא שוורים. Anashim v'lo shevarim Not to tell you
פטור מדמי ולדות. Patur midmei velados. דמי ולדות Dmei velados we get
from בעל השור נקי. Ba'al ha-shor naki. So what do you do
with the אנשים ולא שוורים Anashim v'lo shevarim דרשה? Derasha? Here's what
they do with it. אלא אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו, Ella Abaye veRava
de'amri tarvaihu,
where am I?
אנשים אין אסון באשה יענשו. Anashim ein ason be'ishah ye'aneshu. By men,
you know, if people are fighting, then as long as there's no
loss of life, you pay for the damages. יש אסון באשה לא
יענשו. Yesh ason be'ishah lo ye'aneshu. If the woman died, so it's
not נפש תחת נפש Nefesh tachas nafesh like the פסוקים Psukim say,
because it's manslaughter, it's accidental. So what's the reality though if the
woman dies? It turns it into a case of קים ליה בדרבה
מיניה. Kim leh bederabbah mineih. It turns it into a case of,
oh, there was a death, now even if you're not חייב מיתה
Chayav misah because it wasn't intentional, it's קים ליה Kim leh and
you're not going to pay for any financial payments. הא יש אסון
באשה לא יענשו. Ha yesh ason be'ishah lo ye'aneshu. Okay? So it
tells you a principle of קים ליה. Kim leh. You only pay
if there's no death. If there's a death, no payment. That's what
the פסוק Pasuk is telling you. And then it tells you ולא
שוורים. Velo shevarim. You wouldn't say that by an ox. Okay? Because
ולא שוורים דאף על גב דיש אסון יענשו. Velo shevarim de'af al
gav deyesh ason ye'aneshu. Even if the ox caused a loss of
life, okay, יענשו, Ye'aneshu, you still pay for damages, because you don't
say a principle of קים ליה Kim leh by an ox. So
if the ox basically caused a loss of life, you would still...
now the funny thing is you wouldn't pay for...
wouldn't you say like there is a קים ליה?
Kim leh? Well, there's not a קים ליה, Kim leh, you would
pay... the thing is in this פסוק Pasuk what you learn from
the simple פסוק Pasuk of this case of an intentional goring or
whatever, is that you don't pay for the loss of life. That's
not קים ליה. Kim leh. It's a point I've said before, תוספות
Tosafot makes this point multiple times. The basic point is that you
don't pay for, you know, you assess value in terms of injury
but not for loss of life. Loss of life is either you
execute the person or you send them into גלות, Galus, or if
their ox did it, then if it's the third time, you pay
כופר, kofer, but there is no compensation that is assigned for loss
of life. That's not a קים ליה Kim leh principle. Okay, unlike
the... But actually by the way from what I understand the personal
injury lawyers say that if you're going to seriously injure somebody you're
better off killing them because from a financial perspective because the pain
and suffering and all of that you pay if you've injured them
but if you actually just kill them then you don't pay for
pain and suffering you only pay for like their earning potential and
so on. It's a you actually wind up you wind up paying
less anyway. But in the הלכה Halacha you don't pay what?
You'd better be paying you
wind up well that's true that's true anyway I guess if it's
negligent loss or something. Anyway so in the הלכה halacha you do
not pay for you don't pay for there's not a civil payment
for loss of life okay? But that's not the קים ליה Kim
lei principle. And what we learn out here is by the case
of אנשים Anashim if there was let's say a cost to pay
for the fetus but a woman died you're not going to pay
for the fetus because but by an ox if they gore somebody
so yes we already know that if it's not a מועד Muad
you're not going to pay for the loss of life but you
also want to pay for you will pay for other damages. You
don't say קים ליה Kim lei by the ox. So you'll never
pay for loss of life but you will pay for other damages
and that's what this פרשה Parsha. teaches us. Yes Rabbi Do?
Maybe you said this or I didn't understand. You don't pay for
the fetus conceptually you don't pay for the fetus because it's like
an or considered in this case like an organ of the woman's
body?
Right and that's why you need a separate פרשה. Parsha I didn't
say that explicitly. I said but because what I was actually saying
was even if you consider it part of the woman's body I
don't understand why in paying damages for the woman's body you're not
paying for the loss financially for the fetus because a woman's body
a woman goes for more on the slave market pregnant as not
pregnant. Right so the פסוק Pasuk
of אנשים Anashim teaches you don't pay.
Yes but he was asking about what the why it's you anyway
already pay נזק Nezek why do you need a separate פרשה Parsha
for paying for דמי ולדות? Dmei vlados? So the very fact that
you need a separate פרשה Parsha for paying דמי ולדות Dmei vlados
says the straight נזק Nezek payment on the woman's body does not
pay for her being worth more on the slave market as a
pregnant woman which is a strange idea. Like I don't know why
you need a separate פרשה for דמי ולדות Dmei vlados and why
an ox is exempt for דמי ולדות Dmei vlados it should all
just be נזק Nezek for the woman. I don't know. Okay.
I also thought that maybe this accidental death of the woman is
treated as if it were murder as opposed to negligent because in
a pregnant condition one should know that she's more vulnerable.
That might be might be but still negligent it's still not murder.
I mean you're right might be more negligent. But anyway okay so
but that's what we're learning now. Okay let's read it again. יש
אסון באשה
לא יענשו. Yesh ason bisha lo yeanshu. But okay, אנשים אין אסון
באשה יענשו, Anashim ein ason bisha yeanshu, יש אסון באשה Yesh ason
bisha if there's ever a loss of life לא יענשו Lo yeanshu
you don't pay for any other types of damages. ולא שוורים Vlo
shvarim wouldn't be true by oxen דאף על גב דיש אסון Daf
al gav dyesh ason even if there is a loss of life
יענשו Yeanshu you're still going to pay maybe not for the cost
of the life but you will pay for other damages. הדר כתב
רחמנא בעל השור נקי לפטור Hadar kesav rachmana baal hashor naki lfatur
and then it tells you בעל השור נקי Ba'al ha-shor naki? to
tell you that you are פטור Patur from דמי ולדות Dmei vlados
meaning so what I would have thought would have been what? I
would have thought the ox gores okay and because of the comparison
to אנשים it's telling me there's still going to be a payment
for damages even if there's a loss of life. Oh so that
means so he won't pay for the loss of life but let
him pay at least for the fetus which I in this case
isn't considered a loss of life it's just considered damages okay because
that's not yet considered a life. So based on that I would
have been prepared to have the ox pay for the fetus not
for the woman's life but for the fetus and then it tells
me בעל השור נקי ba'al ha-shor nakei. you know what oxen don't
pay for fetuses either okay? So the פסוק Pasuk of אנשים ולא
שוורים Anashim v'lo shevarim tells me you don't say קים ליה Kim
lei by an ox and the פסוק Pasuk of בעל השור נקי
ba'al ha-shor nakei. says you don't pay for the fetus even though
the fetus is not considered the payment for a life it should
just be a normal damages nevertheless you don't pay for the fetus.
So what are you arguing?
Okay nothing in this case.
Okay so I guess what I'm not understanding is if the ox
is stoned why isn't that the same thing as קים ליה דרבה
מיניה? Kim lei derabbah minei? The ox is stoned therefore it's not
paying.
I mean isn't that like a so that's you're right so even
though we say מיתת הבעלים כמיתת השור Misas habaalim kmisas hashor and
we have these ideas that the ox is sort of being you
know tried for murder right nevertheless you're it's a good point right
that's the חידוש Chiddush but we still wouldn't say קים ליה Kim
lei by an ox. Okay so that's exactly what it's telling you.
So if an ox gores and destroys somebody's clothes in the process
of killing them okay they're not going to pay כופר kofer, because
it's the first time they're not going to pay for a cost
of life we don't have compensation for loss of life the ox
will get stoned but even though the ox will get stoned the
owner will still pay for the for the destroyed clothing because your
the ox at the end of the day isn't paying it's the
owner paying so you're not going to say קים ליה Kim lei
by a case of an ox that's what this is teaching you.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא Ela so
the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רב אדא בר אהבה Matkif lah
rav ada bar ahava rav ada bar ahava challenges אטו באסון תליא
מילתא Atu bason talya milsa what you think the exemption here from
payment is just by by people is just by the fact that
there was a loss of life that's a קים ליה Kim lei
case? בכוונה תליא מילתא Bkavanah talya milsa it's about intention. Now what
does he mean? So רש״י Rashi says there's a long תוספות... Tosafos...
gives another explanation. רש''י Rashi says that רב אדא בר אהבה Rav
Adda bar Ahava holds some very unusual positions. Number one is he
rejects the idea of קים ליה Kimlei unless your act is a
person is actually doing an act of murder. If it was an
unintended act of manslaughter, he doesn't hold of תנא דבי חזקיה, Tanna
d'vei Chizkiya, it's not קים ליה. Kimlei. קים ליה Kimlei is only
in intentional act of murder. Number one. Number two what he holds
for that person. Number two what he holds is that actually you
do pay financial compensation for loss of life. So for רב אדא
בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava actually, if somebody due to manslaughter,
unintentional manslaughter, took a life, there would be no קים ליה Kimlei
and there would be a payment, financial payment for the loss of
life. That's what רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava says.
So according to him, he's saying you can't read the פסוק Pasuk.
to say, oh by people, once there's a loss of life you're
not paying. That's not true. By people, even if there's a loss
of life you'll pay. You're not going to say קים ליה Kimlei
and you'll pay for the loss of life. Okay? So here's how
he's going to read the פסוק. Pasuk: אלא אמר רב אדא בר
אהבה, Ela amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, אנשים here's how to read
the פסוק: Pasuk כי נתכוונו זה לזה, Ki nishkavnu zeh la-zeh, אף
על גב שעשאון באשה ייענשו. Af al gav she-asa'un b'ishah ye'anshu.
By people if they're trying to kill one another, and you killed
ראובן, Reuven, then, and, you know, and the woman accidentally got injured
or there was a miscarriage or even she died, you'll still pay,
because there's no קים ליה Kimlei on the woman. The murder was
only, you know, what ראובן Reuven did to שמעון. Shimon. The injury
or the loss of life of the woman was a separate thing.
As he's killing
שמעון, Shimon, he's actually, he knocked שמעון Shimon and whatever and accidentally
he fell on the woman and the woman died as a result.
Nevertheless, it's only קים ליה Kimlei on what he did to שמעון.
Shimon. It's not קים ליה Kimlei on what happened to the woman,
and therefore that was like a separate act or something, and therefore
he'll pay the injury or he'll pay for loss of life to
the woman. It's a very radical position, very limiting position on קים
ליה. Kimlei.
Only שמעון Shimon who's actually killed.
Well, certainly he'd pay for
the
woman if שמעון Shimon wasn't killed.
No קים ליה Kimlei on collateral damage.
There's no קים ליה Kimlei on any time, the only קים ליה
Kimlei is if I'm doing an act of murder to that person,
then I קים ליה Kimlei on anything that I owe that person,
on any type of obligation to that person. Okay, okay, כי נתכוונו
לאשה עצמה, Ki nishkavnu l'ishah atzmah,
the one case that you'll say קים ליה Kimlei is if they
actually tried to kill the woman. In that case, לא ייענשו. Lo
ye'anshu. They won't pay for her loss of life or for the
fetus. That will be a case of קים ליה. Kimlei. That's true
by people. ולא שוורים, V'lo shevarim, but by oxen, דאפילו נתכוונו לאשה
עצמה, De-afilu nishkavnu l'ishah atzmah, even if the ox intentionally killed a
woman, which is a classic case of
שור הנסקל, Shor ha-Niskal, ייענשו, Ye'anshu, you won't pay for the loss...
well actually according to him you will pay for the loss of
life, because he actually has an idea, right, that you do pay
a financial payment for the loss of life. So you don't have
קים ליה Kimlei by oxen, and you will pay for the loss
of life. That's a big חידוש, Chiddush, right? So fine, there's no
כופר, kofer, but there's still going to be a financial payment. Okay,
so one minute, let me just check רש''י, Rashi, hold on. Let
me just check
רש''י. Rashi. One
minute.
Okay, so anyway, so it says like this, כתב רחמנא בעל השור
נקי דפטירי. Kasav rachmana ba'al ha-shor naki de-patiri. So then it tells
you בעל השור נקי ba'al ha-shor nakei to tell you actually that's
not true, that at least by דמי ולדות D'mei vlados you're not
going to pay. Okay? That there's still no liability by דמי ולדות.
D'mei vlados. I re-read רש''י, Rashi, it's not 100% clear this point
that רש''י Rashi would say that there would be the financial payment
by the woman, but anyway, but that's basically what he's saying. He
has a much more limited idea of קים ליה. Kimlei. You would
only say קים ליה Kimlei when there was a direct act of
murder. In that case of a direct act of murder by the
ox, it's true there's no קים ליה. Kimlei. That's what you learn
by, everybody agrees that what you learn by the פסוק pasuk at
this stage of אנשים ולא שוורים is there's no קים ליה Kimlei
by an ox. Okay? Whatever your scope of קים ליה Kimlei is,
whether it's
unintentional, etc., whether it's only intentional, you would not say it by
an ox, but you might still have said דמי ולדות D'mei vlados
by an ox. And that's what בעל השור נקי Baal Hashor naki.
comes to tell you is that you don't say דמי ולדות D'mei
vlados by an ox. So that's how we get them working together.
Number one is there's no דמי ולדות, D'mei vlados, that's בעל השור
נקי. Baal Hashor naki, Number two, אנשים ולא שוורים there's no קים
ליה Kimlei by an ox. All right. תניא כוותיה, Tanya kevaseh, okay,
וכן כי אתא רב חגאי מדרומא V'chen ki asa Rav Chaggai mi-daroma
when רב חגאי Rav Chaggai came from the south, אתא ואייתי מתניתא
בידיה asa v'ayti masnisa b'yadeh he brought the following ברייתא baraita. in
his hand, כוותיה דרב אדא בר אהבה kevaseh de-Rav Adda bar Ahava
to be like רב אדא בר אהבה. Rav Adda bar Ahava. Okay.
Fine. So that's one thing, that we learn out that you're פטור
Patur from דמי ולדות D'mei vlados which as we said is strange
why it's considered separate than the נזק done to the woman, but
you're פטור Patur from דמי ולדות, D'mei vlados, that's the דרשה, Drasha,
and what we learn out from אנשים ולא שוורים is something else,
that you don't say קים ליה Kimlei by an ox. All right.
So now, what have we learned out from בעל השור נקי? baal
hashor naki We might... Might as well list the things we're learning
out from בעל השור נקי. baal hashor naki, One is
אסור בהנאה assur be-hana'ah
and the עורו oro is the אסור, assur, like basically you don't
get any benefit from a שור הנסקל. shor ha-niskal. Okay, the other
is no חצי כופר chatzi kofer by a שור הנסקל. shor ha-niskal.
The third one is no דמי ולדות, dmei vlados, okay, ever by
an ox. Okay, that's number three. Let's see what number four is.
Okay, תניא אידך, we've done another ברייתא. braisa בעל השור נקי. baal
hashor naki Finally Rabbi Akiva who's been so critical of everybody else's
דרשה, drasha, let's see what Rabbi Akiva says. רבי עקיבא אומר נקי
מדמי עבד. Rebbi Akiva omer nakei mi-dmei eved. Okay, so this is
another no דמי עבד. dmei eved. These cases are basically even though
it's not exactly the case of the שור הנסקל, shor ha-niskal, okay,
these were directly שור הנסקל shor ha-niskal cases, right? They killed a
person, you're not going to pay half כופר, kofer, that's a case
of killing a ישראל. Yisrael. That's a classic שור הנסקל. shor ha-niskal.
Okay, these are not cases of a classic שור הנסקל, shor ha-niskal,
but they're close. There's a loss of life. So this is killing
a fetus. Okay, so you understand that we're not just randomly picking
cases, we're still putting them in the context of loss of life.
And this is killing a slave. Okay, so what would I have
thought? I might have said that if you kill a slave, maybe
you will pay, maybe you'll pay the שלשים של עבד, shloshim shel
eved, right? Because what do we know? What happens if a שור
shor actually what does what do we say? If an ox is
a מועד mu'ad and it kills a slave, you don't pay כופר,
kofer? right? What does the פסוק pasuk say? Right? It says אם
כופר יושת עליו או בן יגח כמשפט הזה אם עבד יגח השור
או אמה כסף שלשים שקלים יתן לאדוניו. im kofer yushas alav o
ben yigach ke-mishpat ha-zeh im eved yigach ha-shor o ama kesef shloshim
shekalim yitein la-adonav. So if it kills a slave by a מועד
mu'ad it's 30, it's not כופר, kofer it's 30 כסף. kesef. So
maybe we know that there's no חצי כופר chatzi kofer by a
תם, tam? but maybe a תם tam will still pay the 30
of an עבד. eved. Okay, so you have to tell me it
doesn't pay the 30 of an עבד. eved. All right, everybody got
it? That's a reasonable question. Okay, here it tells me a מועד
mu'ad pays the 30 of an עבד. eved. Do I know not
a תם? tam That's what בעל השור נקי baal hashor naki. is
telling me. So the Gemara says ונימא רבי עקיבא לנפשיה. u-neima Rebbi
Akiva le-nafshei. So before we get to understanding this idea of maybe
you would have paid the שלשים של עבד, shloshim shel eved, why
doesn't Rabbi Akiva say his own critique to himself? והלא הוא עצמו
אינו משלם אלא מגופו הביאו לבית דין וישלמו לך. ve-halo hu atzmo
eino meshalem ela mi-gufo havi-uhu le-beit din ve-yishalmu lach. So what Rabbi
Akiva said to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, yesterday, he says you don't
need to tell me that a תם tam? doesn't pay when it
kills somebody, it's not going to pay חצי כופר. chatzi kofer. Of
course it can't pay. The model of a תם tam is paying
from the body of the animal. So the animal is worth nothing,
you're going to stone it. That was Rabbi Akiva's critique. You remember
that? So why does Rabbi Akiva need to say you don't pay
דמי עבד dmei eved if it's a case of תם? tam. Of
course you can't pay דמי עבד, dmei eved, the תם tam? isn't
worth anything. Okay, let him say it to himself. So the Gemara
said אמר שמואל בר אבא יצחק כשקדם בעליו ושחטו. amar Shmuel bar
Abba Yitzchak keshe-kodem ba'alav u-shechato. There could be a case where you
could have paid from the body of the ox. The owner slaughtered
it before it was the גמר דין gmar din that it was
a שור הנסקל. shor ha-niskal. So remember, it only becomes forbidden once
the בית דין beit din passes judgment that it's a שור הנסקל.
shor ha-niskal. If they slaughtered it beforehand it never becomes a שור
הנסקל. shor ha-niskal. So in that case maybe you pay it from
the meat. And that's why it has to say don't pay it.
So מהו דתימא לישתלם מיניה mahu de-teima lishtalem minei I might say
you have to pay שלשים shloshim of an עבד eved from the
meat now of the animal so you prevented it from being a
שור הנסקל, shor ha-niskal, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that you
don't. הואיל ובר קטלא הוא, ho'il u-var katla hu, since it was
deserving of death, אף על גב דשחטיה af al gav de-shachte even
though you slaughtered it, לא ישתלם מיניה lo yishtalem minei you're not
going to pay.
Okay, and we had a לימוד limud earlier. It's the same לימוד
limud we had earlier.
No, but before we had a לימוד limud of not חצי כופר.
chatzi kofer. Here we're saying no דמי עבד. dmei eved.
No no, but we had this issue of slaughtering it beforehand.
Yeah, there we had slaughtering it after the גמר דין gmar din
that it was still אסור. assur. Here that was the חידוש chidush
earlier that after גמר דין gmar din even if you slaughtered it
it's אסור. assur. Here we're saying if you slaughter it before גמר
דין gmar din it's מותר, mutar, it never gets to גמר דין.
gmar din. So therefore since now there's meat that's going to remain
מותר mutar and there's value here maybe you'll pay דמי עבד dmei
eved קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that you don't. Okay, now
we're saying one minute. So now the Gemara's going to say fine.
But yes?
If somebody slaughters his animal knowing that he's supposed to bring it
to the court, does he get punished for doing that?
No. I mean he just gets out of it. Yeah, exactly. He
managed to beat the system. Okay. I mean you know it's an
interesting question like I don't know is there some דין בשמים din
be-shamayim and it's sort of subverting the whole case, but there's no
earthly punishment for that. Okay, so the Gemara says like this,
okay. אי הכי ei hachi for Rabbi Akiva... לרבי אליעזר נמי כשהקדימו
ושחטו. l'Rabbi Eliezer nami keshekidmu ushchato. Why did רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer
if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva already knew that there was a scenario
of שחט shechting it before גמר דין gmar din and therefore we
could discuss whether it pays דמי עבד, dmei eved, why didn't רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? give that scenario when he had to discuss not
paying חצי כופר? chatzi kofer? There is a scenario where it's worth
something. You שחט shechted it ahead of time.
הכי נמי, hachi nami, you're right.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva knew that there was this answer of שחט
shechting it, so why was he bothering רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? Where
is there value in this ox? What do you mean רבי עקיבא?
Rabbi Akiva You know you could get value out of the ox
if you שחט shechted it ahead of time. So why are you
asking רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer וסבר דילמא איכא טעמא אחרינא דעדיף מהאי.
v'savar dilma ika taama achrina de-adif mi-hai. He, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva's,
said to himself, I got one scenario where you could be paying
from this ox. You שחט shechted it ahead of time. But you
know what? I'm not so happy with that answer. So therefore when
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is talking about telling me you do or
you don't pay, I'm going to challenge him. Maybe he'll have a
better answer than I do.
Okay, so עדיף מהאי. adif mi-hai. ונימא ליה. v'neima lei. Okay, ונימא
ליה v'neima lei and you know, and he'll say it to him.
לרבי
אליעזר נמי לשני ליה שקדמו ושחטו. l'Rabbi Eliezer nami lisheni lei she-kidmu
v'shachto. So then
okay, so we understand רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, who knew the answer
that you could turn it into value by jumping the gun and
שחט shechting it. He still challenged רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer to see
if רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would come up with a better answer.
But why didn't רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's just give this answer, which
we're basically saying was רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's answer better than this?
אמר לך, amar lach, yes, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's answer was better
than jumping the gun and שחט shechting it. התם הוא דנתכוין להרוג
את הבהמה והרג את האדם. hatam hu de-nitkaven l'harog et ha-beheimah v'harag
et ha-adam. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's answer, remember what was רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer answer where the ox will still have value? That it
actually gored a person and it wasn't trying to gore the person.
It was trying to gore an animal, so it wasn't a שור
הנסקל. shor ha-niskal. Do you remember that case? Yeah, people, yes, vaguely.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's said what would be the case that it
would pay כופר, kofer that it might pay חצי כופר chatzi kofer
and it's not a שור הנסקל, shor ha-niskal, it still has value.
It tried to kill an animal and killed a person. So we're
not going to stone it because it was unintentional, but it would
still pay כופר, kofer and therefore maybe it will pay חצי כופר.
chatzi kofer. That was רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer case. Okay, so that
was his answer to how we could be discussing that this animal
still has value, not that you jumped the gun and שחט shechted
it, but that the animal never became a שור הנסקל shor ha-niskal
because it was an unintentional killer, not an intentional killer. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. התם הוא דנתכוין להרוג את הבהמה
והרג את האדם, hatam hu de-nitkaven l'harog et ha-beheimah v'harag et ha-adam,
דשור לאו בר קטלא הוא כלל. de-shor lav bar ktalah hu klal.
There, the ox was never deserving of being stoned. It was never
a
שור הנסקל. shor ha-niskal. דסלקא דעתך אמינא נתחייב, de-salka daitach amina nitchayev,
there I would think, okay, let's get you some payment out of
the body of the ox. The ox is completely excluded from the
שור הנסקל shor ha-niskal category. אצטריך קרא למיעוטיה, itzterach kra l'mautei, and
you needed a פסוק pasuk to exclude it. אבל הכא דמעיקרא בר
קטלא הוה, aval hacha de-mei'ikara bar ktalah hava, but here where really
the ox is deserving of being stoned, you just managed to subvert
the law by שחט shechting it ahead of time. לא צריך קרא.
lo tzarich kra. A case where the standard scenario would be the
ox would be stoned, in that case it's obvious that the תורה
Torah would not be making you pay. Okay, that the תורה Torah
would never have assumed that you would be paying in that case
of cases, אף על גב דשחטיה, af al gav de-shachtei, even though
you שחט shechted it. So what are we saying? We're saying that
both רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva? and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer are learning
from the פסוקים pesukim to exclude a certain payment from the body
of the ox that's a תם. Tam One is you don't pay
חצי כופר chatzi kofer and the other is you don't pay דמי
עבד. dmei eved. Where do you get payment from the body of
the ox if it's a תם? Tam So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's
said that it was not a שור הנסקל, shor ha-niskal, it killed
by accident. And רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva would say you jumped the
gun and שחט shechted it ahead of time. And what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer answer is actually
a better answer than רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva because רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer gives a scenario where fundamentally it was never deserving of סקילה
skilah and therefore there would be more of a basis to say
you actually can be paid from the body of the ox. Okay,
but either way they're saying you don't have certain payment by a
שור תם shor tam and they're giving scenarios where you might still,
the body of the ox would still have value. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
ורבי עקיבא נמי ודאי הכי הוה. v'Rabbi Akiva nami vadi hachi hava.
So according to רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva that's clearly true also that
a better scenario is never having been a שור הנסקל shor ha-niskal
to begin with.
אלא אמר רב אסי האי מילתא מפי גברא רבה שמיע לי ומנו
רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא. ela amar Rav Assi hai milsa mi-pi gavra
raba shmiali u-manu Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina.
No, no, no, wait, wait. I got a good explanation why רבי
עקיבא Rebbe Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* was not bothered with this issue, why
he challenged רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, and he himself wasn't bothered with
the issue that there's no value to the ox. I heard this
from a great man, and that's רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* בריה *breih*
דרבי *d'Rabbi* חנינא *Chanina*. סלקא דעתך אמינא *Salka da'atach amina*, הוה אמר
*hava amar* רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, here's a really good answer except
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to challenge it, but it's so
good before it gets challenged. הוה אמר *Hava amar* רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva*, אף תם Tam שחבל באדם משלם במותר נזק שלם *af tam
shechaval b'adam m'shalem b'mosar nezek shalem*, right? Remember, who remembers this? According
to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, if a תם Tam *tam* injures a
person, you pay full damages, not half damages. Anybody vaguely remember that?
No, it was a pop quiz. Okay, so it's perfect! רבי עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva* thinks that if a תם Tam *tam* injures a person,
you pay full damages. So therefore you would think רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* is able to think you would pay שלושים של עבד shloshim
shel eved, *shloshim shel eved*, because he says I don't think a
תם Tam *tam* when it's injuring or killing a person is paying
from the body. I think it's paying full, and presumably it's paying
like a מועד Muad, *muad*, it's not paying from the body. So
I could think that it should pay דמי עבד dmei eved. *d'mei
eved*. And therefore you need a פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* to exclude it.
But you, רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, that you think a תם Tam.
*tam* is standard and pays half, because you said חצי כופר chatzi
kofer, *chatzi kofer*, if you think it pays half, you're thinking it's
paying from the body of the animal. Well, if it's a שור
הנסקל shor haniskal. *shor haniskal*, there's no value to the body. So
if you think it's paying half, you think it's paying from the
body and רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says I don't understand why you
need a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, the ox isn't worth anything. But I
think you should be paying full דמי עבד Eved. *d'mei eved*, because
I think when an ox gores a person, it pays full, and
it's not paying from the body of the animal. So of course
it doesn't bother me that it's a שור Shor הנסקל *shor haniskal*,
I think you should be paying full. Wait a minute, it's such
a great answer, but the גמרא *Gemara* now throws it out. The
גמרא *Gemara* says one minute, אמר ליה *amar lei* רב זירא *Rav
Zeira* לרב אשי *l'Rav Ashi*, והא *v'ha* רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* לגזיזי
*ligzeizei*? But רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* already blunted his, you know, his
punch. Where did he do that? מדתניא *Mi-d'tanya* רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
אומר *omer*, יכול ישלם מן העלייה min ha'aliya, *yachol y'shalem min ha'aliyah*?
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says although I say when a תם Tam,
*tam* injures a person it pays full, it's not totally like a
מועד Muad. *muad*. Maybe it should pay from cash and not from
the body of the animal. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar *Talmud lomar*, כמשפט
הזה יעשה לו K'mishpat hazeh ye'aseh lo, *k'mishpat hazeh ye'aseh lo*, this
is what you'll do to it. מגופו mi-gufo. משלם ואינו משלם מן
העלייה min ha'aliya, *migufo m'shalem v'eino m'shalem min ha'aliyah*, that even when
it pays full, it's only paying out of the body of the
animal, not from cash. I don't know if you remember that. So
although רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says you pay full, and that's why
he thinks you would pay full דמי עבד Eved *d'mei eved*, he
doesn't think there's an idea of half when it injures people, you
still have an answer to the problem that רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
should say to himself, but if you're only paying out of the
body of the animal, the animal isn't worth anything.
Yeah, what happened to the position
that a תם Tam, *tam* pays nothing and חצי chatzi. נזק *chatzi
nezek* is a קנס *knas*? That would not be מגופו mi-gufo. *migufo*.
Yes it would. Whether it's קנס *knas* or ממון *mamon*, it's מגופו
migufo, *migufo*. That's never debated.
קנס *Knas*, how is קנס *knas*...
that's the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*, וחצו את השור החי וחצו את כספו
*v'chatzu et hashor hachai v'chatzu et kaspo*. This is the nature of
this קנס *knas*, that you're paying מגופו migufo. *migufo*, that you're either
half owners or you have a lien, it's limited to גופו *gufo*.
Nobody debates any of those הלכות *halachot*, the question is just whether
it's conceptualized as ממון *mamon* or as קנס *knas*. If anything, that
works better with קנס *knas* because it's more arbitrary and weird. If
it's a standard ממון *mamon* payment, why should it have those rules?
Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says, okay, so it was a
great point to remind us that רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says when
it injures a person it's full, which is why רבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* says חצי כופר kofer, *chatzi kofer* but רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
thinks you would pay the full דמי עבד Eved *d'mei eved*. But
we're still bothered with the fact that, you know, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* should have just,
why was he דראיינג *draying* רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* a קאפ *kopf*
about the fact that the animal wasn't worth anything? It's the same
issue for him. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this, okay,
where are we? אלא אמר רבא *Ella amar Rava* איצטריך *itztrich*. סלקא
דעתך אמינא *Salka da'atach amina*, no, here's why רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
thought in his הוה אמינא hava amina. *hava amina* that you would
pay a full שלושים שקל shekel, עבד Eved. *shloshim shekel eved* and
you would not pay from the body. Why רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
was still bothered, he didn't like any הוה אמינא hava amina. *hava
amina* of paying from the body of the animal, because the animal
wasn't worth anything, but in his הוה אמינא hava amina. *hava amina*
of paying שלושים שקל עבד Eved *shloshim shekel eved*, he thought you
wouldn't pay from the body of the animal. Why is that? Here's
the reason. I would have thought to say, הואיל ומחמיר בעבד יותר
מבן חורין *hoil u'machmir b'eved yoter mi'ben chorin*. Since in general the
תורה Torah *Torah* is stricter by the death of a slave than
by the death of a free person if he was killed by
an ox. How is that true? שבן חורין יפה סלע נותן סלע
She-ben chorin yafeh sela nosein sela, שלושים נותן שלושים *she'ben chorin yafeh
sela notem sela shloshim notem shloshim*. By a person who is gored
by an ox, you pay based on the value of the person,
whether it's one סלע *sela* or שלושים *shloshim*, if he's worth one
you pay one, thirty you pay thirty. ועבד יפה סלע נותן שלושים
*v'eved yafeh sela notem shloshim*. So but by a slave, it's more
strict, you always pay thirty. Now of course the irony is, but
also if he's worth a hundred you pay thirty. What makes you
say thirty is more strict? Thirty is more arbitrary, sometimes more strict,
sometimes more lenient. But whatever the answer is, we're saying look, there's
many cases in which the idea of thirty, maybe it's assumed that
thirty is a high payment. is a sort of is strict. So
the תורה Torah is having this flat payment, this strict approach by
an עבד. Eved, So maybe included in that strict approach by an
עבד Eved would be the idea that they would pay, a תם
Tam. would pay, and a תם Tam would pay מן העליה, min
ha-aliya, not מגופו. migufo, Okay. So therefore I might think, משלם נמי
דמי עבד מן העליה. meshaleim nami d'mai Eved min ha-aliya. So it
gives me a הוה אמינא. hava amina. Once the תורה Torah is
being somewhat arbitrary here, okay, maybe it would be saying even a
תם Tam should pay and it should even mean מן העליה. min
ha-aliya. Now by the way, using just the phrase strict is not
so helpful. I think here a better phrase is arbitrary, okay? Meaning,
if it's paying thirty, which is arbitrary, then that goes to the
point that Rabbi Dov was making a minute ago, which is, if
it's an arbitrary thirty שקל, so then maybe it doesn't... once it's
being arbitrary in one way, it doesn't matter how much the slave
is worth, let it be arbitrary in other ways. It doesn't matter
if it's a תם Tam or if it's a מועד, Muad, it'll
and it's not... we're never going to pay מגופו. So clearly an
arbitrary thirty payment regardless of circumstances. So the same way regardless of
circumstances is regardless of how much the עבד Eved is worth, then
regardless of whether the שור Shor is a תם Tam or a
מועד. Muad Okay, so that actually is a reasonable הוה אמינא. So
I actually would have thought once the תורה Torah is being arbitrary,
even a תם Tam, should pay it and it should pay מן
העליה. min ha-aliya.
Of course if I'm the בעל השור Baal Hashor I'm going to
argue against that.
Yeah, but you're not the... but you're just the layperson, we're the
rabbis making the rules, so we think that that's a
הוה אמינא. Okay.
כתב רחמנא בעל השור נקי. kosav rachmana Baal Hashor naki. Okay. תניא
כוותיה דרבא. Tanya k'vosei d'Rava. We actually have a ברייתא like this.
בעל השור נקי. baal hashor naki, Rabbi Eliezer omer נקי מדמי עבד.
naki mi-dmei Eved. You don't pay the עבד. Eved. ולא דינו? V'lo
dino? You could use... you should say you should pay for the
עבד by a תם. Tam You could learn it out from a
קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, at least a logical derivation. הא דחייב בעבד
וחייב בבן חורין, Ha d'chayav b'Eved v'chayav b'ven chorin, so you're חייב
chayav by a slave, by כופר, kofer when it's a מועד, Muad
and you're חייב chayav by a free person. מה כשחייב בבן חורין
חלקת בו בין תם למועד, Ma k'shechayav b'ven chorin chilakta bo bein
Tam l'Muad, I mean the דין din that you should be exempt,
excuse me. Why does Rabbi Akiva have to tell me from the
פסוק pasuk you're exempt, I could logically learn out you're exempt. The
same way by a free person you don't pay any payment when
it's a תם, Tam אף כשחייב עבד נחלוק בו בין תם למועד.
af k'shechiyav Eved nachlok bo bein Tam l'Muad. So when you're paying
by a slave, you should also pay, you should also say you
shouldn't pay. If you don't pay by a free person who gets
gored by a תם, tam. you shouldn't pay by a slave who
gets gored who's a תם. tam. That makes sense, right? ועוד קל
וחומר. V'od kal v'chomer. And it's even stronger than that. מה בן
חורין שנותן כלו שויו, Ma ben chorin she-nosein kulo shavyo, by a
בן חורין ben chorin that's weightier, here it looks the idea that
you pay the exact value as a weightier demand. The fact that
a free person you pay the exact value, even though it's that
weighty, חלקת בו בין תם למועד, chilakta bo bein Tam l'Muad, you're
going to say that you make a distinction between תם tam and
מועד Muad and you don't pay when the ox gores when the...
when a תם tam, gores a free person. עבד שאינו נותן אלא
שלשים, Eved she-eino nosein ela shloshim, so here's looking at שלשים shloshim
as a leniency. By a slave where it's only שלשים, shloshim, right,
it doesn't go up as... it's not... it can't be a very,
very high value. It's limited to thirty. The תורה goes lighter by
a slave. אינו דין שנחלוק בו בין תם למועד? Eino din shenachlok
bo bein Tam l'Muad? How much more so should we say that
when a תם tam gores it should not pay. If a תם
tam, gores a free person doesn't pay, how much more so if
it gores a slave it shouldn't pay. So why do you need
a פסוק? pasuk, You can just learn it out. Now by the
way we should also point out that part of the problem here
is that the תורה is not clear. By the time it gets
to right... this is תם, tam. כי יגח שור את איש, ki
yigach Shor et Ish, right, והועד בשור נוגח v'hu'ad bashor nogach וכופר
יושת עליו, v'kofer yushas alav, by the time it gets to אם
בן יגח או בת יגח, im ben yigach o bas yigach, are
we talking about a מועד Muad, still or are we talking about
everything we just said before, right? כמשפט הזה יעשה לו,
right? Does that mean oh if it's a מועד Muad that kills
a בן ben or בת bas you do the same thing? Maybe
it means if it's whether a תם or a מועד, Muad if
it kills a בן ben or בת bas you do everything we
said before. When it gets to עבד, אם עבד יגח השור, im
Eved yigach ha-Shor, are we talking only about a מועד muad or
are we talking about anytime a שור gores a slave you pay
thirty? A very reasonable read of the פסוק pasuk, is that whenever
an ox gores a slave you pay thirty, right, that's a very
reasonable read. Okay, but the גמרא is saying no, קל וחומר kal
v'chomer I could have figured out not. Okay, so the גמרא
says לא, lo, no, I could argue the opposite. מחמירני בעבד יותר
מבן חורין. Machmirani b'Eved yoseir mibben chorin. I could say I would
be more strict. שבן חורין יפה סלע נותן סלע, שלשים נותן שלשים,
shloshim nosein shloshim, a בן חורין ben chorin could be less than
thirty. עבד יפה סלע נותן שלשים, Eved yafeh sela nosein shloshim, an
עבד is always thirty which sometimes is more strict. And again, as
I would say, the point is also it's more arbitrary. And since
it's arbitrary, maybe I will always pay whether it's an... whether the
ox is a תם or a מועד muad. since the whole idea
of paying of an עבד is arbitrary. יכול יהא חייב, Yachol yehei
chayav, תלמוד לומר בעל השור נקי, נקי מדמי עבד. naki mi-dmei Eved.
You don't pay the value of an עבד. So this you gotta
admit, this is obviously a great answer and this explains why Rabbi
Akiva... it's great because of the פסוק. pasuk All of this stuff
wasn't in the פסוקים. pesukim. Rabbi Akiva is looking at the פסוק
pasuk and he says... Down here it tells me that you pay
שלושים של עבד, and I don't know if it's talking about a
מועד muad. or even a תם. That's not clear from the פסוק,
pasuk and maybe if it's just arbitrarily saying it,
maybe it's מן העלייה, it's not מגופו, even if it's a תם.
Very reasonable read of the פסוק, pasuk right? There's not the standard
הלכה of a שור תם shor tam paying חצי. The פסוק pasuk
is telling you if an ox gores a slave, you pay thirty,
maybe it doesn't matter תם or מועד. muad. And that's when you
need to say בעל השור נקי that no, you don't pay דמי
עבד.
What is that פסוק pasuk telling you according to רבי עקיבא?
That you don't pay that, this פסוק pasuk. is only talking about
a מועד. That בעל השור נקי, you don't pay, and this is
telling you that that's only talking about a מועד. But it was
a great הוה אמינא. The פסוק should be talking about a תם,
and you would pay straight מן העלייה, not מגופו. So when רבי
אליעזר says חצי כופר, kofer. רבי עקיבא says, how could you be
talking about paying מגופו, how could you be trying to use a
תם model? The ox isn't worth anything, it's a שור הנסקל. But
I'm saying that this פסוק should include תם, okay? And this בעל
השור נקי tells me that that פסוק doesn't include תם. All right,
that was the end of the דרשה drasha of בעל השור נקי.
Let's, you don't understand this?
I know, I do understand it. I mean, I don't know if
I could explain it an hour from now, but I understand it,
your explanation was really clear. I have a crazy question. Yes? I'm
sorry, I apologize, I gotta ask this. Like, it's such a
sharp read, that
רבי עקיבא
was so sharp, right?
Like who else was reading texts like this?
I don't know the answer to that.
You know what I'm saying?
It's just astounding.
Right, right, yeah.
I mean, once you realize that they're really dealing, I mean, that's
a lot of the מדרשי הלכה midreshei halacha as you, when you
realize that they're dealing with inherent ambiguities in the text itself. Okay,
let's get, let's read a little bit more. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan,
והמית איש או אשה, vehemit ish o isha, we're moving on! Okay,
we did כי יגח שור את איש או את אשה
ומת, ki yigach shor et ish o et isha vamet,
and then והמית שורו vehemit shoro
והמית את איש או אשה. vehemit et ish o isha.
So now we're going through, we did a דרשה drasha on בעל
השור נקי, לא יאכל את בשרו. lo yeachel et besaro. Now we're
going to do והמית איש או אשה. vehemit ish o isha.
Okay, a string of מדרשי הלכה. midreshei halacha.
Yeah, right. Exactly, exactly. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rebbe Akiva, וכי מה
בא זה ללמדנו? vechi mah ba ze lelamdenu?
Why does it have to tell me a man or a woman?
Why would I think it would make a difference? אם לחייב על
אשה כאיש, im lechayiv al isha keish, if it's to tell me
you're just as liable for a woman's life as a man's life,
הרי כבר נאמר, harei kvar neemar, כי יגח שור את איש או
את אשה ומת, ki yigach shor et ish o et isha vamet,
right? כי יגח שור את איש או את אשה. ki yigach shor
et ish o et isha. So I already know up here that
you're just as liable, so here too you should also be just
as liable. Okay, it's clear from the framing of the whole thing
is we're treating the death of a woman and the death of
the man the same. אלא הקיש אשה לאיש, ela hikish isha leish,
connect them in the following way: מה איש נזקק ליורשיו אף אשה
נזקקת ליורשיה. mah ish nizkak leyorshav af isha nizkaket leyorsheiha.
The person that got killed is dead. Who collects the כופר? kofer
So if a man is dead, who are you going to pay
the כופר to? His heirs, his kids. So it's telling you if
the woman was dead, who do you pay the כופר to? Her
kids, her kids. Now with a, why her kids? How about her
husband? Her husband normally inherits her. So that's going to be now
our question. וסבר רבי עקיבא לא ירית לבעל? vesavar Rebbe Akiva lo
yarit labaal? Does רבי עקיבא think that the husband doesn't inherit from
his wife? והתניא, vehatanya, ויורש אותה. veyarash otah.
It says that you give it to the לשארו הקרוב אליו, lish'ero
hakarov elav,
to the relative that's closest, ויורש אותה. veyarash otah. אותה otah means
inherit a נחלה, nachala, the inheritance. But we're going to do a
דרשה, drasha, he shall inherit her. מכאן שהבעל יורש את אשתו, mikan
shehabaal yoresh et ishto, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rebbe Akiva. So there's
actually a debate whether when a husband inherits from his wife, is
that דרבנן derabbanan or דאורייתא? deoraisa? But רבי עקיבא is learning it
from a פסוק. He thinks it's biblical that a husband inherits from
his wife. So how could you learn from אשה לאיש isha leish
that you give the כופר to her heirs, her kids? You should
be giving it to her husband. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish,
לא אמר אלא בכופר, lo amar ela bechofer, הואיל ומשלם אלא לאחר
מיתה. hoil umeshalem ela le'achar mita. Yeah,
the only type of time this would go to the kids and
not the husband would be כופר, because the whole obligation of כופר
comes when? After she's dead. Let me ask you a question: after
she's dead, is she this man's wife? No.
So he only, a man only inherits from his wife money that
was in her you know like under you know in her property,
in her control, money that she had when she died. Then all
the money that she had when she died passed on to her
husband. But if she inherits something after her death, if money comes
to her after her death, then that goes to her heirs because
it makes sense. Her heirs are still more related to her after
her death than her husband, right? The husband isn't a blood relation.
The bond there was a bond in life. Even after she's died,
she still gave birth to her kids. Like they still descend from
her. Okay, so therefore money that comes to the woman
Even when we're thinking about ירושה. Yerusha. Right. So let's, right, let's
just read this. חבין
משעת נגיחה למיתה.
Chovin mish'at
negichah l'misah. והיה לו ראוי. V'hayah lo ra'uy.
It was money that was fit to come to her, but didn't
come to her yet. ואין הבעל נוטל בראוי כבמוחזק. V'ein haba'al notel
b'ra'uy k'b'muchzak. And the husband doesn't inherit stuff that was fit to
come to his wife the same way he does the stuff that
was already under her control. He only inherits property that was already
under her control when she died. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the
reason? אמר קרא. Amar kra. The verse says, ואם איש או אשה
השור יסקל וגם בעליו יומת אם כפר יושת עליו. V'im ish o
ishah hashor yisakel v'gam ba'alav yumat im kofer yushas alav.
So first he talks about the person dying, stoning the ox, which
means the person is already dead, and then paying the כופר. So
you see that the כופר payment comes only after the person is
dead. And therefore because it's coming after the person is dead, we
already know from another גמרא that the husband only inherits property that
his wife had when she was alive. But this, that comes after
she's
dead, the heir defined after death, is the kids, who descend from
her, not the husband who their bond no longer exists now because
she is now dead. Okay. So we will pick up with this
tomorrow. Rabbi?
Yes.
What would you say is the theology of the